<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The last testimony of that faithful servant of the Lord and minister of Jesus Christ, Richard Farnworth whereunto is prefixed a brief testimony concerning his life, death and travels &amp;c. : to which is added a few words of exhortation unto those that believe in the light of the the Lamb : published for the consolation of the household of faith .. / by a companion of those who hold the word of God and testimony of J[e]sus Christ and suffer for the same, Josiah Cole.</title>
            <author>Coale, Josiah, 1632?-1668.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1667</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40935</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F488</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R27355</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09818693</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09818693</idno>
            <idno type="VID">44177</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40935)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 44177)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1356:31)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The last testimony of that faithful servant of the Lord and minister of Jesus Christ, Richard Farnworth whereunto is prefixed a brief testimony concerning his life, death and travels &amp;c. : to which is added a few words of exhortation unto those that believe in the light of the the Lamb : published for the consolation of the household of faith .. / by a companion of those who hold the word of God and testimony of J[e]sus Christ and suffer for the same, Josiah Cole.</title>
                  <author>Coale, Josiah, 1632?-1668.</author>
                  <author>R. F. (Richard Farnworth), d. 1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1667.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>R. F. --  (Richard Farnworth), d. 1666.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:44177:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:44177:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Laſt Teſtimony OF That faithful Servant of the Lord, and Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>RICHARD FARNWORTH.</hi> Whereunto is Prefixed A brief Teſtimony concerning his <hi>Life Death,</hi> and <hi>Travels, &amp;c.</hi> To which is added A few words of Exhortation unto thoſe that believe in the Light of the Lamb.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed for the Conſolation of the houſhould of Faith; and for the ſtopping of that mouth which is opened in Blaſphemy againſt God, his Tabernacle and them that dwell in Heaven.</p>
            <p>By a Companion of thoſe who hold the Word of God, and Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Jeſus Chriſt, and ſuffer for the ſame: <hi>JOSIAH COLE.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Then I heard a voice from Heaven, ſaying unto me, Write; The dead which dye in the Lord are fully bleſſed, even ſo ſaith the Spirit, for they reſt from their labours, and their works follow them,
<bibl>
                  <hi>Rev. 14.13</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1667.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:44177:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:44177:2"/>
            <head>A Brief Teſtimony concerning the Life and Death OF That faithful Servant of the Lord, and Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Richard Farnworth,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>FOraſmuch as it hath pleaſed God Almighty (after the long night of woful groſs Darkneſs, Apoſtacy and Ignorance, which hath been over the Nations, amongſt thoſe who have had a Profeſſion of Chriſtianity) again to make known and manifeſt, the true, new, and living way which leads unto Life Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, even by and through the Revelation and Operation of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Power, and Word of Life, in the hearts of a Remnant, whom (in this our day) he firſt reached unto and viſited, and raiſed up to be Witneſſes thereof; that by them it might be born Teſtimony unto, amongſt thoſe who were ſtrangers to it, and that thirſted af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it, that ſo thereby they alſo might receive the manifeſtation and knowledge thereof, for want of which many periſh, and are ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to the way of Life; having only (at beſt) a Form of godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs without the Power: In which dead Forms, or outſide empty Profeſſions, ſome are at eaſe and reſt, as though they were in the true Heaven that ſhould never paſs away, and ſome are at reſt and at eaſe without any profeſſion, living in all uncleanneſs; unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and abomination; and ſome cannot find reſt in either.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:44177:3"/>The faithful and true Witneſs of God being awakned in their Hearts and Conſciences, which takes the falſe peace from them, and lets them ſee the emptineſs of all outſide profeſſions, which are without Life and Power, and alſo the abominations, and vanities of the world, and makes ſin exceeding ſinful to them: And by this true and faithful Witneſs are deſires, and breathings, and pantings begotten in their hearts after the knowledge of God &amp; Chriſt, after fellowſhips &amp; acquaintance with the Father and the Son<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which deſire cannot be ſatisfied without the knowledge &amp; enjoyment of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lord, and of the light of his countenance. And for this cauſe many run to and fro, and wander like Sheep gone aſtray from the true Sheepherds fold, and are wearying themſelves upon the barren Mountains, in vain looking thereunto for Salvation, and ſeeking the living amongſt the dead, and ſo ſpend their labour for that which doth not ſatisfie. And in theſe ſeveral ſtates and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions aforeſaid, the whole Chriſtian world lieth, who are not turned to the Light and Spirit of Jeſus in themſelves; and true reſt and ſalvation cannot be found by them, until they return to the Light and Power of the Spirit of God in their own hearts, which is that whereby a diſlike of ſin is begotten in them, and alſo deſires af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Life and Salvation; and freedom from ſin is thereby begotten; and that is it alone which can anſwer every deſire, which is begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by its ſelf. Well,</p>
            <p>But when it pleaſed the Lord to reveal the Son of his Love, and to make known his eternal Power (in theſe latter days) for the rending of the Vail of darkneſs that had long been over the heart, by which he cauſed the Light to ſhine out of darkneſs, which gives the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his own glory; he did not then give the knowledge and manifeſtation thereof unto all People, but he choſe certain Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, whom he raiſed up to declare of the manifeſtation of this Power, and to preach the Word of Life nigh, in the heart and in mouth; and he furniſhed them with Armour of Righteouſneſs, and with all ſpiritual weapons; which were mighty through him, to break down the ſtrong holds of Iniquity, &amp; the ſpiritual wickedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that were in the high places; and impowred them as Inſtruments in his hand to turn many from darkneſs to the Light, that the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of God they might come to ſee; and the Work of God greatly proſpered in their hands; and multitudes were brought to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:44177:3"/>the acknowledgment of the Truth, to the ſaving of their Souls: and though they met with great oppoſition, and perſecutions; by the Emiſſaries of Sathan, even in all Quarters where they came; yet that was not prevalent to hinder the proſperity of that Work whereunto they were called of God, but it ſtill proſpered, and doth ſtill proſper, to the ſpreading of the unchangeable Truth abroad, even as is ſeen at this day.</p>
            <p>And of this number whom God Almighty at the firſt raiſed up by his Power for this Work aforeſaid, the late deceaſed <hi>Richard Farnworth</hi> was one, concerning whom the chief occaſion of this my preſent writing is; that ſo a Teſtimony concerning him, and of what the Lord did by, and through him, may remain upon Record for Generations to come; and that this preſent Generation of the Juſt, may ſee and hear his laſt Teſtimony, which proceeded from his own mouth a little before his departure out of the body; and I doubt not, but thereby the Conſolation and ſpiritual Comfort of the Houſhold of Faith will be added unto.</p>
            <p>And, for theſe Cauſes, I could not well reſt ſatisfied in my ſpirit without taking in hand to publiſh theſe things; though I well know that there are many living Witneſſes that knew the Life, Labours, and Travels of the ſaid <hi>R. F.</hi> who are the Seal of his Miniſtry: And alſo the many Writings of his own, which remain upon Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, will ſpeak forth to thoſe, who are of a true Spiritual under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, what he was; yet notwithſtanding all theſe things were in my mind, and divers of other Conſiderations, which occaſioned me to defer the publication hereof ſo long as till now; yet being I could not be ſo clear in my duty towards God and my Brother, in neglecting to give forth this my Teſtimony concerning him, and in ſuffering ſo precious a Teſtimony, as his laſt was, wholly to be put in oblivion, I have with freeneſs and cheerfulneſs of heart un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken it.</p>
            <p>And when it pleaſed God to manifeſt his Eternal Power in the heart of the aforeſaid <hi>R. F.</hi> it is well known unto many how ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually it wrought in him; inſomuch, that although he was (before) a man of great abilities, and parts, and knowledge, accounted of among men, even excelling many of his equals; yet he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and willing, in obedience to the Power of God, to become a Fool to the World, and to be ſtript and emptied of his own wiſdom
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:44177:4"/>and knowledge, (which ſtood in the ſtate faln from God and his Power) and to ſuffer the loſs of all worldly reputation and favour, and the pleaſures and delights thereof, that he might win Chriſt Jeſus, and be found his Servant, clothed with the Righteouſneſs of Faith, preferring the ſimplicity that is in Chriſt, beyond all worldly wiſdom and honour whatſoever; and his Sufferings for the ſake of Chriſt, beyond all worldly reputation; and ſo great was the change that was wrought in him, that he became a wonder a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt many; and the Word of God and his Power was great and mighty in him, and through him; in which he was ſent forth by the Lord (who had manifeſted himſelf unto him) to preach the Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Goſpel to the poor, and to declare of that great Power of God, of which he was made a Witneſs, and of the Effects of its operation; and ſo powerfull was his Meſſage and Teſtimony, that many were begotten into a firm belief thereof; and believing the Report, were turned from Darkneſs to the Light of Jeſus, with which they were enlightned, and from Sathans power unto the Power of God, which wrought mightily in their hearts, to the changing of their minds and affections from things that are below, towards things that are above all that is fading and corruptible, and to the bringing of Life and Immortality to light in them: And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they were attended with many foul temptations, becauſe of their obedience to the Truth and Light of the Spirit of Grace, and brought in many diſtreſſes in their paſſage from Death unto Life, yet was he ſo experienced in the Depths and Subtilties of Sathan, and alſo in the Dealings and Goodneſs of God in ſuch conditions and eſtates, that he had obtained the tongue of the Learned, and could (as oft times he did) ſpeak words in Seaſon, to the ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the weak, and refreſhing of the weary; and to the revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of that which was near ready to faint: So that he was in the Lords hand, even as a father to the fatherleſs, and as eyes to the blind, and feet to the lame; and the eye that truly ſaw him, bleſſed him; and the ear that heard him, gave witneſs unto him: for through the Power of God which enabled him, he delivered the poor and the needy, and built up many (that believed) in their moſt precious Faith, and confirmed them therein: And went about from place to place, through the Land of his Nativity, turning many from Darkneſs to Light, and confirming the Churches, and doing good:
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:44177:4"/>And his Service was very great for the Lord in his day; for he was ſo furniſhed with Heavenly Wiſdom and Underſtanding through the Grace of God; and alſo ſo ſeaſoned thereby, that his Patience, Meekneſs, and Humility exceeded many: And although God had ſo endued him with heavenly Vertues and Abilities exceeding ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, yet was he not pufft up therewith, neither ſought to exerciſe lordſhip over thoſe that were weaker, and younger then himſelf, but gave place unto any that had the leaſt Gift of God, to exerciſe; ſo that through the Spirit of Meekneſs and Humility, with which he was adorned, he was exceeding lovely and beautifull, and the hearts and ſouls of many were affected therewith, who in ſimplicity thirſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed after Righteouſneſs, and ſuch waited for him, as for the Rain, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whom his Doctrine ſo dropped: Yet nevertheleſs he was terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Worker of Iniquity, and the Sword of his mouth was very ſharp, for the Word of God was therein; and when he had to do with any who oppoſed the Truth and VVay of Life and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, which we profeſs and walk in (as oft-times he had) his VVeapon was very ſharp to them, and they were not able to reſiſt the VViſdom of the Spirit by which he ſpoke; for thereby he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded their wiſdom, and broke their weapons in pieces; ſo that they were oft ready to Blaſpheme God, becauſe of the plague that it was to them; and a Conqueror he was over the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Beaſt and falſe Prophet, againſt whom he made VVar in Righteouſneſs, in and through the Power of the Lamb, in whoſe Spirit he hath finiſhed his Teſtimony and Courſe in the Faith.</p>
            <p>And as the Enemies of the Truth of God were many, and in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ſhapes, that this valiant Souldier of the Lamb had to encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter withal, ſo he was always furniſhed with Armor and VVeapons, fit for the VVork and Service in which he was exerciſed, by which he was enabled to encounter with, and Conquer all: But at laſt, that his Armor and VVeapons might be proved to be ſufficient to encounter with the Enemy of Truth, in all kind of Appearances and Transformations, it was his lot with me, and divers others of the Servants of the Lord, to be engaged againſt the Enemy of Truth, who had transformed himſelf into the likeneſs of an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of Light, and under a ſeeming pretence of appearing on the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of God and his Cauſe, &amp;c. and againſt Formality and Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, &amp;c. begun ſtrongly to oppoſe the Truth of God, and the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:44177:5"/>Miniſtry thereof in and through his Servants and Meſſengers (who have approved themſelves as the Miniſters of God, and as his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors) and to cry againſt our Aſſemblies and manner of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and our Exerciſe therein, (as only Formal;) in which we have alwayes found the glorious Preſence, Power and Majeſty of the Lord amongſt us, refreſhing, comforting and ſtrengthening of us, even acording as our hearts and ſouls can or could deſire; ſo that we were engaged to juſtify the Lord, in oppoſition to that gainſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpirit of deluſion, by which many were beguiled and led away after Satan, to their hurt: And in our Teſtimony for the Lord, and againſt that ſelf-ſeparating gainſaying ſpirit, the Power of the Lord did greatly accompany and aſſiſt us, and was as greatly with us, as in any ſervice that he had called us unto; <hi>The ſincere and upright in heart (who have kept their firſt Love, and their firſt Faith) are Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of it;</hi> and how in Love we laboured for the reſtoration of thoſe who were beguiled through the craft of the Enemy; and for the preſervation of thoſe who hitherto have eſcaped his ſnare, that is well known to many witneſſes. But if none were ſenſible of it, the Lord he knows, and is witneſs, that in ſincerity of heart (in the Name of the Lord) towards God and his People we were exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; and in our labour and travel for them, the Bleſſings of the Lord and his Peace, and the comfort of his Spirit, did poſſeſs and fill our hearts beyond the underſtanding of the world, although ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, towards whom we were ſo in love exerciſed, could not believe, but ſome withſtood our Teſtimony, and kicked againſt it in their hearts, and reſiſted the Counſel of God againſt themſelves, to the grief and ſorrow of our hearts.</p>
            <p>Therefore it pleaſed the Lord, in Love, Mercy and good Will to his Servant, my <hi>dear Brother, R. F.</hi> that his Travels, Burdens, and grievous Sufferings might be put to an end; and that our teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony for the Lord might be ſealed with the Life of his Servant againſt that Antichriſtian intruding Spirit of Oppoſition, which laboured to intrude its ſelf into the Church, to ſit as Ruler and Judge there. I ſay, for theſe cauſes, <hi>and for none contrary hereunto,</hi> it pleaſed God to viſit my <hi>dear Brother, R. F.</hi> and to take him out of the Body; at which, I perceive, ſome who are ignorant of what the Lord intended thereby have rejoyced: But let ſuch know, that they have made a wrong application of the dealing of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:44177:5"/>Lord therein; by which they have hardned themſelves, inſtead of being humbled through that which was ordered of God for their hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation and good; and if poſſible that ſuch may yet ſee, and turn to the flock of the Companions of Chriſt: And alſo that the flocks who are (and have remained) in the true Fold may be refreſhed thereby, I ſhall here inſert the <hi>Last Teſtimony</hi> of the aforeſaid <hi>R.F.</hi> which was given by him, a very ſhort ſpace before his departure out of the body, in the preſence of ſeveral good Friends; at which time in the name, ſtrength, and power of God, he was moved to ſit up in his Bed, and ſpake (concerning the Love of God and concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Teſtimony, againſt the aforeſaid antichriſtian, intruding, factious ſpirit) with as much ſtrength, power and freeneſs of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, as at any time he had done in the time of his outward health. Whoſe words were as followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Friends, God hath been mightily with me, and hath ſtood by me at this time, and his power and preſence hath accompanied me all along, though ſome think that I am under a Cloud for ſomething; but God hath appeared for the owning of our Teſtimony, and hath broken in up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me as a flood, and I am filled with his Love, more than I am able to expreſs; and God is really appeared for us. If God himſelf had come down and ſpoken as a man, he could not have ſpoke more clearer to us than he hath done, by the many Teſtimonies from Heaven in his People con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this thing. Therefore I beſeech you Friends, here of this City of</hi> London, <hi>(live or dye) be you faithful to your Teſtimony which God hath committed to you, and as it ariſeth in your hearts, be faithful to the Lord therein.</hi> After which he was ſilent for a little ſeaſon, and then his mouth was again opened in the Name and Power of the Lord, even as before, and he ſpake very preciouſly unto Friends concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the things before mentioned, teſtifying of the greatneſs of the Love and Power of God, of which he was made partaker, and which he then felt; and of the preciouſneſs of the Truth, which he had with us born witneſs of; and exhorted them to faithfulneſs and ſtedfaſtneſs therein, and to ſingleneſs, that nothing might be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to creep in of another nature, to intermix therewith, ſaying, <hi>No Lincy-woolcy Garment must be worn,</hi> &amp;c. with much more to that effect, which cannot be remembred. And having thus given his laſt Teſtimony, as a Seal unto all the former Teſtimonies which he had given for the Lord, and on his behalf, in about two or three hours time after, being filled with the Peace and Love of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:44177:6"/>declaring, (as himſelf ſignified) he departed this Life, even like a Lamb, and ſlept with his Fathers and Brethren, and is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into everlaſting reſt with the Lord.</p>
            <p>And this may ſerve alſo as a ſufficient Teſtimony, to ſtop the mouths of all who vaunt themſelves in his death, as though he had been ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away in Judgment and Diſpleaſure of the Lord, becauſe of his appearing on the behalf of God againſt that antichriſtian ſpirit of oppoſition, which contends againſt our Meetings, and Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and the manner of our exerciſe in the Worſhip of God, as Formal, &amp;c. And let ſuch know, that if his being removed prove a Judgment unto any, it will be to them, who rejected the Mercies of God by him tendred to them, and have thereby hardned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt the Lord and his Servants, and have made a wrong application of the dealings of the Lord with his Servant, even as thoſe who know not the purpoſe of God therein; and ſo have ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves not to be the Friends of God, as <hi>Abraham</hi> was, from whom God did not hide the thing that he intended; but let ſuch yet repent, if a place can be found for them.</p>
            <p>And ſo let all my dear friends every where, who believe in the Light of Jeſus, and who have taſted of the Love, Goodneſs, and Power of God, dwell in the ſence and feeling of his Love and Power, and let nothing divert or turn aſide the minds of any from perſevering in that pure holy way of Life, which they are called to walk in, and in which the daily renewings of the peace and good will of God is witneſſed; neither let any be ſlack or remiſs, in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming that antient, godly, Chriſtian practice of Aſſembling your ſelves together in the Name and Fear of the Lord, foraſmuch as ye know the exceeding benefit and advantage that ye have received thereby, becauſe of the Lords Appearance amongſt us, who, acord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Promiſe hath not failed us unto this day; but his Name and Power hath been great amongſt us, and ſtill is, opening the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of his Kingdom, and revealing of the vertue of his Life in our hearts and ſouls, by his own Spirit, to our great refreſhment and comfort; ſo that we have not at any time been <hi>ſent empty away,</hi> who have in ſincerity <hi>thirſted after him,</hi> and in faithfulneſs <hi>waited for his appearance;</hi> which is ſufficient to encourage all to perſevere in that godly practiſe of meeting together with all integrity, without wavering. And foraſmuch as our aſſembling together at this day, is the great thing that the Enemy of Truth ſtrikes at in all his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:44177:6"/>of all kindes, in which he appears againſt us; it behoves all to ſtand and be faithful therein; that the Cauſe of God may not be betrayed by any, through their declining from that godly Practice and duty, that the enemy may not be encouraged thereby to vaunt againſt the remnant that are faithful, to oppoſe them therein alſo; but rather, through your faithfulneſs and ſtability, the enemy may be diſcouraged in his enterpriſes, and put to flight, that you may be Conquerours over him, and may tread Satan under foot, and may reign with the Lamb for ever.</p>
            <p>And my Friends, conſider the faithfulneſs of many of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the Lord, who <hi>loved not their lives unto death,</hi> who <hi>are gone before,</hi> who <hi>preached</hi> and <hi>made known</hi> the <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>way</hi> of <hi>Life to you,</hi> how they <hi>laboured</hi> and <hi>travelled</hi> amongſt you, in the <hi>name</hi> and <hi>ſtrength</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> to <hi>beget</hi> you unto <hi>God, and to build you up in the moſt preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Faith;</hi> and how they <hi>exhorted you time</hi> after <hi>time</hi> to that <hi>godly pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice,</hi> of <hi>Aſſembling together,</hi> and how they gave <hi>Example</hi> and <hi>Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent therein</hi> as well as <hi>Exhortation thereunto.</hi> Nay, have not divers of them <hi>laid down their Lives (not counting them dear to them)</hi> for that very <hi>Practice</hi> of <hi>Aſſembling together?</hi> Yea, certainly they have ſo; ſome in <hi>Priſons,</hi> and ſome <hi>otherwiſe.</hi> Oh therefore, my <hi>Friends,</hi> this <hi>Duty</hi> of <hi>Aſſembling together,</hi> ought not to be <hi>flighted;</hi> nay, hath not the preſent <hi>Liberty</hi> that we do <hi>enjoy,</hi> in our <hi>meeting together, coſt the Lives</hi> of many? was it not with <hi>the blood of many</hi> (of them that <hi>bore</hi> the <hi>ſame Teſtimony</hi> which <hi>we bare</hi>) that this <hi>preſent Liberty hath been purchaſed?</hi> and ought not <hi>this Liberty then to be prized, and made</hi> a <hi>right Uſe of? I am jealous with a godly Jealouſie, that all who are concerned, do not rightly weigh, ponder, and conſider theſe things;</hi> but I deſire all to conſider it, and let not that <hi>Teſtimony</hi> fall (by the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lience of any) which hath been <hi>ſealed</hi> with the <hi>Lives of ſo many of Gods Servants</hi> and <hi>Meſſengers,</hi> whoſe <hi>Knowledge</hi> and <hi>Underſtanding</hi> in the <hi>Way</hi> and <hi>Myſteries of God,</hi> was not inferiour unto any that are left behind, and yet they <hi>chearfully offered up their All</hi> for that <hi>Teſtimonies ſake.</hi> Therefore, my <hi>Friends,</hi> he <hi>diligent</hi> and <hi>faithful</hi> to the Lord, walking in his <hi>Covenant</hi> of <hi>Light,</hi> which will be a <hi>true Guide</hi> unto you, and an <hi>Inſtructor,</hi> and will <hi>keep your Deſires freſh to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Lord,</hi> and your <hi>Love one towards another;</hi> ſo that you will be conſtrained to <hi>Come together,</hi> and to <hi>wait together</hi> upon the <hi>Lord,</hi> to receive <hi>refreſhment</hi> from his <hi>preſence,</hi> which you will <hi>ſee</hi> and <hi>feel</hi> in the middeſt of you, as your <hi>hearts</hi> are <hi>kept</hi> in his <hi>Fear;</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:44177:7"/>not into <hi>conſultation</hi> with <hi>fleſh</hi> and <hi>blood,</hi> nor into <hi>reaſonings</hi> which will ſay, <hi>Thou needeſt not go to Meetings, becauſe thy Teacher is preſent in all places,</hi> and ſo will draw thee into <hi>negligence</hi> of <hi>meeting</hi> with the <hi>Children of Light;</hi> for if thou give heed unto ſuch reaſonings, thou wilt ſoon find, thy <hi>Love will wax cold</hi> towards the <hi>People of God,</hi> and thou wilt loſe the ſence of the <hi>Teachings</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> who is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in all places; for although he be in all places preſent, yet hath he <hi>ordained</hi> and <hi>appointed,</hi> that his People ſhould <hi>Aſſemble themſelves together</hi> to <hi>wait</hi> upon him, and to <hi>worſhip</hi> him, and hath given the <hi>promiſe</hi> of his <hi>Preſence</hi> unto ſuch that do ſo. But if <hi>any draw back</hi> from anſwering his <hi>requirings, his ſoul will have no pleaſure in them:</hi> and ſuch will <hi>dye</hi> as to God, &amp; will become as <hi>dry</hi> and <hi>withered branches,</hi> and their <hi>Love will decay,</hi> &amp; <hi>wax cold,</hi> and they will not have a <hi>ſight,</hi> nor a <hi>ſence</hi> of the <hi>Omnipreſence</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> nor of his <hi>Teachings,</hi> though they may <hi>talk</hi> of it, as <hi>multitudes</hi> do at this day, who are altogether <hi>ſtrangers</hi> thereunto, further than by hear-ſay. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore once more I ſay unto you all, <hi>Be faithful to the Lord in your ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral meaſures and ſtations, where the Lord hath ſet you, and be diligent in that godly Practice of Aſſembling your ſelves together, in which a Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony for the Lord is born, which many have laid down their Lives for, and let none make their blood of no effect, by ſlighting Meetings; the preſent Liberty for which hath been purchaſed through the ſhedding their blood, but let all meet together, and being met, wait upon the Lord in faithfulneſs, that you may feel the Springs and Fountain of Life opened amongst you, and in the middest of you, that you may be refreſhed and ſtrengthened, and may grow, and be enabled to encounter with your ſouls Enemy in all his appearances, and may put him to flight, and may tread Satan under foot, and reign as Kings on Earth, and as Conquerours, to the praiſe of his Name (who hath called you, that he may take delight to dwell amongſt you, and to do you good) who over all is worthy, God bleſſed for evermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. C.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:44177:7"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
